Yes, that's me.
But I'm sure it could be you too.
Have you ever felt that the little devil on your shoulder talks so loudly that it acts for you?
Eat that doughnut!
No, you shouldn't.
Let me tell you a secret.
That little angel and that little devil aren't actually on your shoulders, but in your gut. And your gut holds… drum roll… the gut microbiota: more than 100 trillion bacteria living in symbiosis with you.
In my thesis, I studied how these angel bacteria and devil bacteria influence the reward system.
The what?
The reward system, in the brain, which gives you a feeling of pleasure when it is switched on by drugs, sex, alcohol…
… but also by fatty and/or sugary food.
This system was very useful for our ancestors who, between two mammoths, went through periods of famine.
But today, it mostly leads to a good deal of fat storage.
Worse still, it can lead to obesity.
Worldwide, 13% of the population is obese, and obesity is associated with the deaths of more than 2.8 million people a year.
People with obesity have a completely dysregulated reward system.
Imagine: when they eat that doughnut, they will feel three times less pleasure than a person without obesity.
People with obesity have an overpopulation of devil bacteria.
We think angel bacteria are able to say: “One square of 90% dark chocolate is enough.”
Whereas devil bacteria will say: “Eat the whole bar!”
In my thesis, I am trying to identify these angel bacteria and devil bacteria, and to understand how they influence us.
In practice, I spend my days with little lean mice and little obese mice.
Unfortunately, I can't give them chocolate and ask them: “So, is it good?”
So I have to train them to press a lever to get sugar.
And we have already discovered one angel bacterium: Akkermansia muciniphila.
When we give this angel bacterium to obese mice, their reward system improves: they press the lever as many times as lean mice to get sugar.
I'm super motivated, because I'm convinced we could help defeat this obesity pandemic.
And that, simply thanks to our little angels, we could all be equal when it comes to pleasure.